早安
我們在這個Wisdom Series
我們說了什麼呢
第一是要敬畏耶穌
敬畏耶穌
Do you guys feel like you have the fear of the Lord in your heart?
The fear of the Lord in your heart
如果我們敬畏耶穌
敬畏神
我們的basis
The basis of our life
Will be a strong foundation
然後Dr. Winley跟我們說了
智慧如何幫助貧窮人
他就說了耶穌的榜樣
And then next, if we listen
We will have wise words
我們要speak with什麼呢
Speak with
Speak with wisdom, yes
但有一個acronym
Speak with
G字頭
We speak with grace
Grace就是godly
Is it right?
Have we asked the Lord?
Is it compassionate?
Is it edifying?
Is it helping others?
如果我們學了這個
我們的words應該要很有智慧
And then next
Sam 傳道
不是,Sam 神學生
跟我們說了wise wallet
God gives us money
We are the stewards of his money
然後我們學了wise relationship
我們要
Relationship是要建的
It's like a house
Foundation is the fear of the Lord
It has to be built
With the cornerstone of Jesus Christ
With the walls of truth
The windows of honesty
The doors of communication
And the roof of love
然後上個禮拜
Eddie 跟我們說了wise education
這個世界的education是好的
但神的education
God's wisdom is greater than any man's wisdom
今天我們會finish with
Wisdom guards our hearts
我會學三樣東西
第一是
為什麼我們要guard我們的heart
我們不guard我們的heart那一詞
會發生什麼事
第三是我們怎樣guard我們的heart
第一
Why guard our hearts?
Let's read proverbs together
1,2,3 in Chinese
1,2,3
It says here in proverbs
Everything flows from your heart
所以我們要guard我們的heart
第一個point
我們的心是source
The source of everything that flows
好像CPU
CPU是stand for what?
記不記得?
有沒有人知道?
Central Processing Unit
因為是Uncle Stanley那年代
是Sark的
所以他知道
Central Processing Unit
我們的心
好像Central Processing Unit
我們的emotion
我們的beliefs
我們的desire
我們的action
是come from我們的心
所以我們要保護我們的心
好像一個waterfall
如果有人在上面pollute the water
之後整個river會怎樣?
會污染
所以我們要guard我們的heart
That is where everything flows from
耶穌也有這樣說
在Luke 6
It says a good man brings good things
out of the good stored up in his heart
And the evil man brings the evil
out of the evil stored up in his heart
我們的心是store什麼呢?
就會有什麼action
好像這個心
on the right
如果我們的心有murder
adultery, theft, false testimony
sexual immorality
我們的心會帶出這樣的action
這樣的words
這樣的motive
所以我們的心
是好像一個treasure
We have to protect our treasure
家裡有沒有人有save?
你放什麼在save裡?
是不是糖果?
是不是零食?
是不是什麼?
最寶貴的東西
你放在save裡
To keep it safe
Treasure
Our heart is like treasure
我們要放在一個save裡
We have to keep it safe
所以第一樣東西
我們為什麼要保護我們的心
因為我們的心是個treasure
It is our CPU
Everything flows from it
第二
It is where the enemy attacks
我們繼續讀中文
1,2,3
(讀中文)
我們的敵手是誰?
Who is our enemy?
蛤?
受敵
受敵是誰?
是魔鬼
Satan desires to attack us
他好像獅子一樣
想attack我們
我們打足球的時候
我們要保護什麼?
要保護什麼?
足球隊那些
龍門
You have to protect the net
你進多少球都好
但你defense不到你的net
那你不可以贏那個champion
Defense wins championships
有沒有聽過這個?
Elias有沒有聽過?
沒有聽過defense
Elias沒有聽過defense
所以我們要守龍門
Goalkeeper, defense
全部要守龍門
不要讓人進球
讓人進球
It is the most harmful to us
敵人想attack我們的net
The enemy wants to attack our heart
為什麼敵人想attack我們?
因為我們的innocence
我們最寶貴的東西
是我們的innocence
Our purity
Physical innocence
Physical purity
Spiritual innocence
Mental innocence
Social innocence
Don Hoa
Lost his innocence
吃了果子之後
那怎麼辦?
他lose了他的physical innocence
之前是沒有罪的
現在有了罪
跟神的關係是怎樣?
It's broken
The social relationship with God
之前跟神很close的
可以聊天的
但沒有了這個innocence
沒有了這個mental innocence
因為有了罪就有什麼?
有什麼mental emotion?
有anger
有guilt
Guilt
With sin comes guilt
And shame
我們要躲起來
為什麼我們要躲起來?
因為我們沒有穿衣服
We were shameful
We were full of guilt
And spiritually
We were broken with the Lord
Spiritually
We are set apart from the Lord
所以兩樣東西
我們為什麼要guard我們的heart?
第一,it is the source
第二,the enemy attacks
我們現在有discussion time
有五分鐘discussion time
Do you think you have been feeding the heart
the things of God
or the things of the world?
Have you been feeding your heart
the things of God
or the things of the world?
第二,how are you guarding your heart?
Mentor,去找細路
一起去有discussion
OK,discuss完沒有?
Good discussion?
有沒有人想分享?
Yoi Wai,你想分享嗎?
OK,OK,好
準備
第一個問題,你分享一下
第一個問題
I don't know what to say
OK,你幫她說
我們覺得都是一半一半
因為我們世上的東西
我們都有很多
例如讀書,都佔據我們的心
我們都有很多對事情的desire
但我們的心也要被上帝慰藉
我們都有不開心,有很單的時候
我們有心靈需要的時候
這個就是沒有其他東西可以補充到
只有上帝的慰藉
OK,好,very good
還有誰想分享?
給點掌聲,Auntie Fiona
Uncle Stanley?
OK,每個星期都Uncle Stanley
好,CY,到你了
我其實很喜歡那邊的答案
不過我們說的有點off topic
Kind of,but
Kind of related
我們說到有一點
Your decision and choices
How do you make the right decisions
Also,有些時候是不對與錯
可能是你自己的will versus God's will
So, how do you differentiate that as well
I think in the world where
we have a lot of worldly desires
and materialistic things
How do you also differentiate that
OK,very good
最後,Eddie,你的group有沒有?
給點掌聲,CY
Eddie,你的group有沒有?
好,Stitch,Stitch,你說
剛才他很有想法
Go ahead,be your question
第二,你覺得呢?
我怎樣把心靈隔開
讀多點聖經,關於Jesus
跟著每天跟Jesus祈禱
然後他會一條路給我走
之後可以成功,in the future
非常好
OK,very good
我們現在會說
我們不隔開我們的心靈會怎樣呢?
What happens when we do not guard our heart
OK,what happens when we do not guard our heart
有沒有人開過車?
有沒有人家裡有車?
家裡有車的時候
是不是有些聲音
或者是甚麼?
是甚麼來的?
或者是有些sign出來,是甚麼來的?
是沒有油,是warning來的
沒有油,或者你未change engine oil
或者你的輪胎沒有氣
它會beep beep beep出來
It is a warning
所以我們沒有guard我們的heart
都會有warning
我們看有甚麼warning
Let's look at proverbs
我們請Gabriel讀第一個
In English
A heart full of pride
Oh
Pride goes before destruction
A haughty spirit before a fall
OK,我們不guard我們的heart
我們會有甚麼?
Pride
Who deals with pride?
驕傲,誰有驕傲?
覺得他們最叻的,是不是?
不用別人教他的
教他踢球,不用教他打機
不用教的
I am the best,是不是?
我look down人的,是不是?
我是矮過人家,但我look down人家的
是不是?
OK,let's read the second one
Josh
Do not let your heart turn to her ways or stray into her paths
OK,第二是甚麼?
我們的heart,如果不guard我們的heart
會有這個世界的試探
這個世界有很多試探
是不是?
有錢,有電話
你現在打的電話,打機,是不是?
然後還有甚麼?
還有甚麼?
可能有drugs,vaping,是不是?
這些東西是harmful我們的body
A lot of temptation
在這個世界,是不是?
OK,next
Let's have Carmen read the next verse
Anxiety weighs down the heart
Anxiety
我們不guard我們的heart
就會有anxiety
We experience anxiety
Yeah,是不是?
有些panic attack
Panic attack,為甚麼?
It reveals that we do not fully trust God
我們不fully trust God
我們會很worry
我們worry,worry
這個不行,這個不行
我們未預備好,這個又不行
是不是?
We worry because we do not fully trust God
這個是warning sign
OK,the last one
我們請這個mentor
The fool says in his heart there is no God
最後,如果我們不guard我們的heart
我們就不會認識神
We will not know God personally
我們不會know God personally
It says in the next verse here
For out of the heart comes evil thoughts
Murder, adultery, sexual immorality, theft
False testimony, slander
These are what defile a person
耶穌就是這樣說
我們不guard我們的heart
我們的心就會有甚麼?
我們繼續被世界影響我們的心
就會有很多不同
It starts with hatred
It starts with lust
It starts with
這個人的東西很漂亮
如果我們有,那會怎樣?
And then it will lead to theft
And false testimony
這個星期有一個很大的incident
Uncle Stanley之前已經pray了
他們有一個investigation
有人at first就說
因為那個bamboo scaffolding
It cause fire very easily
但他們又有investigation
然後發現了甚麼?
是有甚麼?
是發泡膠
First there is styrofoam on the windows or the doors
是很flammable
還有那個netting
那個construction netting
是很flammable
然後就發現了
是個construction company
可能cut cost
是有corruption
然後有個IG post出來
Contractor cut cost
The district councillors were complacent
The Hong Kong government agencies were nonchalant
有沒有人看到這個post?
不只是那個bamboo scaffolding
是有corruption behind this
And so if we do not guard our heart
Eventually it will come out
These things will come out
第三,我們學
我們如何保護我們的心?
How do we guard our heart?
我們會學三個D
The first thing is
Direct our heart
Defend our heart
And depend on the Lord
第一,我們要direct our heart
It says, I have hidden your word in my heart
That I might not sin against you
My son, if you accept my words
And store up my commands within you
Then you will understand the fear of the Lord
我們的心是一個空的杯
我們可以倒purified water
我們可以去海裡倒harbour water
你想喝哪個?
外面的purified water
還是harbour的水很清的
有人覺得很清的
可以喝的
有人說沒有
我們的心,你放什麼進我們的心
就是什麼?
Is what you will store in your heart
這個proverb就說
Store什麼?
Store my words
Store my commands
God's words, God's commands in your heart
那又如何?
那我們就會明白
如何去見慰耶穌
The next, it also says this
I will give thanks to the Lord
Lord with all my heart
That I will tell you of your wonderful deeds
這個詩篇就說
他有感恩
他store什麼在他的心?
是感恩
Thankfulness in our hearts
所以我們要看我們store什麼
Are we storing the word of God?
神的話要在我們的心
還是世界在我們的心?
Are we storing the world
or the word of God in our hearts?
第二,我們store什麼?
我們把神的智慧放在我們的心
還是foolishness in our hearts?
And then number three
Are we storing thankfulness in our heart?
or bitterness?
你有沒有認識一些人
是經常感恩的
很thankful的
他有個attitude
神很好啊
神很bless我們啊
還是你知道那些人
是很bitter的
經常很生氣的
是嗎?
That's what they store in their heart
你看到的
他們的action
reveal到他們的心是store什麼
所以你們今天是store什麼?
你store thankfulness
or you store bitterness
你經常很生氣
這個朋友經常這樣
這個朋友也是經常這樣
經常投訴的
還是你經常有感恩的
我很thankful
這個朋友經常會幫我
這個朋友經常很好
這個朋友也經常很好
What do you store in your heart?
這個很popular的song
就是這樣說
Turn your eyes upon Jesus
And the things of this world
Will grow strangely dim
我們focus在耶穌的時候
這個世界就會disappear
The worries of the world
Will disappear
我們focus在耶穌的時候
這個世界的worries
會disappear
我是去
我在哪裡讀書的?
記不記得?
大學,在哪裡讀大學的?
多倫多大學
University of Toronto
有沒有人想去多倫多大學讀書的?
Anybody?
No? Nobody?
OK,不用去了
It's OK
不用去
是一般般的
可能幾年後
你不用去讀大學
全部都是去查GBT
What's the point of university?
When you just go to check GBT
Look up all the answers
What's the point?
你在家裡做查GBT也可以
我每天上學
是要去TTC
Toronto Transit Commission
它有個study
世界最slow的transit在哪裡?
是Toronto
最slow的streetcar在Toronto
我每天上學是用TTC
又有delay,又很慢
又不知道是不是真的去到目的地
Everyday is an adventure
OK,TTC
我用這個時間去做靈修
每天去做靈修
去認識神多一點
Everyday, I spend time in the word
又有traffic jam,又有delay
就是神和我slow down
去和我說話
Everyday, we need to direct our hearts to the Lord
我們每天是要direct我們的heart
去聽神的說話
我們有沒有呢?
每天有沒有聽神的話?
第二呢?
第一,我們是要direct我們的heart
第二,我們要defend our heart against evil
這個世界有很多不同的聲音
我們學校,我們的朋友
我們的電視,我們的社交媒體
很多不同的聲音
我們要defend我們的heart
撒旦是用我們不同的社會
去try to influence our heart
influence our eyes, what we look at
what we hear,我們聽到什麼
我們想什麼
我們的朋友全部influenced by the world
So we need to defend our heart
我們一起讀
The next verse,我們讀中文
1,2,3
這裡的Proverb就說
我們要turn our ear to my words
我們要留心去聽神的話
如果我們不聽神的話
我們會聽世界的話
然後呢
我們不單止要看我們自己
看什麼,想什麼
我們要看什麼
我們的朋友是不是好的influence
有個study就說
你最好的朋友,最好的四五個朋友是誰?
The sum of these four or five people
It is who you are
如果你四五個最好的朋友
是經常不讀書,又不上學,又遲到
The sum of these four or five friends
就是你了
如果現在不是你,遲早都會是你
是不是
Do you agree?
但是如果你的朋友是好的
經常很健康的,做運動的,很勤力的
上教會的,又在時間上上教會的
又不是經常打遊戲機的
在崇拜之前
You will be the sum of these five friends
但是如果你的這五個朋友
是經常回來遲到的
又打遊戲機的,又不留心的
又不聽導師的說話
Eventually,你就會是這個人
So, our eyes determine what we think and say
Sorry, our ears
我們聽什麼呢?就會想的
所以我們要很小心我們聽什麼歌
你們聽什麼歌?
是不是經常有髒話
又說一些很壞的東西
你聽什麼呢?
就會開始想什麼
你看什麼呢?
你Netflix看什麼呢?
你YouTube看什麼呢?
你就會做什麼
是不是?你會做什麼
你的朋友做什麼呢?
你就會Eventually跟他們做什麼
我們的行動會變成我們的習慣
我們的習慣會變成我們的身分
所以我們的行動
每天都是聽神的話語的
我們每天都會跟別人說好話
encourage別人
Eventually, that will become our habit
and that will become our identity
Our identity is that we follow God's word
and we speak God's word to people
但是如果我們的習慣
是每天遲到的
聽世界說的
做壞事的
And then eventually that will become our habit
and our habit will become our identity
所以我們要Defend
We need to defend our heart against evil
好,我們現在邀請Andrew
Andrew上來,會有個見證
Andrew, welcome
Andrew,我聽說你現在switch去IB
你覺得現在switch去IB怎樣?
有點辛苦
你覺得有什麼辛苦?
IB轉了
你之前是什麼學校的?
我之前是我們學校的DSE
我多了很多continuous assessment
可能我們每一兩個禮拜就有一個test
要溫習很多次
都要習慣
誰在讀IB?
現在有沒有人在讀IB?
有沒有覺得困難了?
有沒有困難一點?
Aiden有嗎?
Andrew,你今天想跟我們分享一個故事是什麼?
我想分享一個故事
就是我有一次沒有保持心態
這件事發生在9月
發生在我有一個比賽
我以為自己可能會很容易贏
但我做的準備可能比我想像中的少
這是什麼比賽?
是一個說話的比賽
在波士頓?
不是,在香港
說話比賽
即是debate
對,那裡
我覺得最難的地方是
因為你現在這樣看下去
是有pride的問題
那時候我覺得pride是一個很內在的事情
很難自己看到
所以是一個心理上的問題
我可能會做得比我想像中的少
到時候你輸了才會發現
你為什麼沒有保持心態
所以你是很有pride
然後你覺得你不需要練習說話
是這樣嗎?
不是,我還是練習了
我只是在猜測一些會發生的事
還有就是
我做得不夠準備
所以我覺得
我們可以做的一件事
或我現在做的一件事
就是我會祈禱
神可以反映我現在內心的問題
還有就是
帶領我如何能夠離開這裡
因為有很多事情是很壞的
然後發生了
因為魔鬼
你剛才也說過
他會祈禱我們不安全
很多事情我們都不想接觸
不想看到
但他就是在攻擊那些東西
所以我們經常會忽略很多這些
所以我覺得這是很重要的
好的,謝謝你提出
魔鬼會攻擊我們
我們需要反映我們的心
還有魔鬼會用什麼東西來對付我們
然後向神祈禱
好,今天我們給予Andrew一個掌聲
非常好
第一個D是什麼?
如何我們防禦我們的心?
記得嗎?
我們要什麼?
直接對付我們的心
我們感受到的
就是我們會從心中得到的
第二個D是什麼?
防禦
我們要防禦我們的心
第一是直接對付我們的心
第二是防禦我們的心
第三我們是要依靠
依靠誰?
我們依靠聖靈
我們一起讀
John 14
1,2,3
耶穌在頂十字架之前
祂就對門徒說
我會給你什麼?
我會給你聖靈
聖靈會和你同在
永遠
神已經派出聖靈來幫助我們
我們每個人都有軟弱
我們每個人都會有試探
我們如何面對這些不同的試探呢?
我們如何面對這些問題呢?
是透過聖靈的力量
我們每個人都很軟弱
所以神是給我們聖靈
第一是什麼?
要懲罰我們
懲罰我們我們的罪
Andrew剛才說
他在比賽之後
他才發現他有驕傲
所以沒有正確的準備
聖靈會懲罰我們我們做錯的事
我們被挑釁的事
第二
聖靈會帶領我們
回到主的身邊
有時聖靈會提醒我們
不如今天我們讀聖經
不如今天我們不要玩遊戲機
我們去聽神的話
好不好?
或者有時聖靈提醒我們
不如我們不要生氣
我們去饒恕我們的朋友
愛我們的朋友
有沒有人試過聖靈提醒他們?
聖靈的指導
聖靈會指導我們
做主的事
第三
聖靈會賜福我們
賜福
中文是什麼?
OK
賜福
是讓我們像基督一樣
讓我們像基督一樣
我們可以自己做嗎?
我們自己可以像耶穌一樣嗎?
有沒有人可以的?舉手
如果我們可以我們不會在這裡
我們哪用在這裡?
每個星期天
我們不能這樣
這就是我們要依靠聖靈
我們自己不能的
所以主耶穌給我們聖靈
去賜福我們
幫我們像基督一樣
希望
當你認識了耶穌
你每天都像祂一樣
你所想的
是主的事
你所做的
對嗎?
那些
那些你愛的人
你愛上了神的每天都像耶穌一樣
你每天都像耶穌一樣
我們要依靠聖靈
我們自己不能的
我們每天都在失敗
是嗎?我們每天都會犯罪
所以我們要依靠聖靈
三個D是什麼?
你和你旁邊的人
測試一下你旁邊的人
三個D是什麼?
OK
OK 三個組 認識嗎?
OK 派一個
三個D是什麼?
第一是什麼?
Direct our heart
然後呢?
Depend 是第三
Defend 是第二
Defend 什麼?
Defend our heart against evil
第三是要
Depend on 誰?
Depend on 聖靈
去幫我們
Convict
Guide and Sanctify our heart
好 我們現在請敬拜隊上來
Let's have a moment of silence
我們為我們自己的心去祈禱
Let's pray for our own heart right now
Let's put our hand on our heart
Let's pray
God will direct our heart
Now place your hands on your eyes
and your ears
Ask God to defend your eyes
Protect your ears and your eyes
From what you see and what you hear
Pray for that
Let's all stand
And we'll finish with this prayer
Father
We thank you
That you sent the Holy Spirit
To guide us
To help us
Help us to depend on the Holy Spirit everyday
This world is wicked and evil
But you are greater
You have conquered all on the cross
May you help us to guard our heart
Guard our innocence
Guard our purity
For Jesus Christ
And the church said, Amen
(字幕由 Amara.org 社群提供)